A Guide to the Appomattox Iron Works and Supply Company Records, 1834-1992
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Appomattox Iron Works and Supply Company Records, 1834-1992
The Library of Virginia
42633
5 cubic feet (12 boxes) and 5 volumes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Marvin T. Broyhill III, Petersburg, Virginia.
Historical Information
The Appomattox Iron Works and Supply Company was founded in 1872 by Esek Steere and E. J. Armstrong, and was located in Petersburg, Virginia. In 1876, Esek Steere and his son Albert Lippett Steere (1872-1931) bought out Armstrong's interest. The company specialized in machinery for the peanut industry, including planters, harvesters, and shellers, and also tobacco industry equipment. The firm also manufactured household products, such as andirons, urns, and firebacks, and also produced bar iron, sheets and plates, and boiler tubes. The company also operated a sawmill, and employed iron and brass founders and machinists. The company ceased to exist in 1972, and the complex was sold to the Godley Land and Cattle Company of North Carolina, but was soon purchased from them by the Historic Petersburg Foundation. The Foundation soon sold it to Frank Peckinpaugh, a retired engineer. The complex was renovated into a living history museum and opened to the public in 1991 by real estate developers Marvin T. Broyhill III and George Pilarinos, but was severely damaged by a tornado that struck Petersburg in August 1993. In 1996, it was sold to the Center for Industrial Preservation.
Scope and Content
Records, 1834-1992, of the Appomattox Iron Works and Supply Company of Petersburg, Virginia, including correspondence, customer orders, receipts, credit reports, price sheets and supply catalogs, account ledgers, weekly time books, day book, and cash ledger. Also included are photocopies of diaries of company founder Esek Steere (1831-1908). The collection also contains files relating to the renovation of the company headquarters into a living history museum in the early 1990's. There is artwork, brochures, clippings, genealogical notes on the Armstrong and Steere families, photographs, proposals and specifications, reports, histories, and information relating to tax credits, grants, and urban enterprise zones.
Contents List
- Accounts, 1900. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Accounts, 1923-1924. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Appleton Manufacturing Company (Batavia, IL). (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Appomattox Basin. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Artwork - Jerry W. Furr, Jr., 1991. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bignall and Keeler Manufacturing Company (Edwardsville, IL). (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Bloomer vs. McQuewan et. als. - Appeal, 1853. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Blueprint - Electric Starting Woodpeckers (Middletown Machine), 18 February 1913. (Box 11)
- Blueprint - Appomattox Iron Works Complex Preliminary Proposal, 11 December 1990. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Broadside, 10 August 1892. (Box 11)
- Brochure. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Building Profiles - Central Core Area. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Cash Ledger, August 1910 - November 1913. (Volume 1)
- Clippings. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Continental Machinery Company (Chattanooga, TN). (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1914 (T-U-V). (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1915 (A). (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1915 (B). (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1915 (T-U-V). (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1916 (A). (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1916 (B). (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1916 (C). (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 1916 (N-O). (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, 1916 (S). (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1917 (A). (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1917 (B). (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Correspondence, 1917 (C). (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Correspondence, 1917 (M). (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Correspondence, 1917 (N-O). (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Correspondence, 1917 (P-Q). (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Correspondence, 1917 (R). (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Correspondence, 1917 (S). (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Correspondence, 1917 (T-U-V). (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Correspondence, 1917 (W-X-Y-Z). (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Correspondence, 1918 (A). (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Correspondence, 1918 (B). (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Correspondence, 1918 (C). (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Correspondence, 1918 (R). (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Correspondence, 1918 (T-U-V). (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Correspondence, 1919 (H). (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Correspondence, 1920 (A). (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Correspondence, 1920 (B). (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Correspondence, 1920 (C). (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Correspondence, 1920 (D). (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Correspondence, 1920 (E-F). (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1920 (G). (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1920 (H-I-J). (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1920 (K-L). (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1920 (M). (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1920 (N-O). (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1920 (P-Q). (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1920 (R). (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1920 (S). (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1920 (T-U-V). (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1920 (W-X-Y-Z). (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1922 (B). (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1922 (S). (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1923 (A). (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1923 (B). (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1923 (C). (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1923 (D). (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1923 (G). (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 1923 (H-I-J). (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, 1923 (R). (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1924 (A). (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1924 (B). (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Correspondence, 1924 (C). (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Correspondence, 1924 (D). (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Correspondence, 1924 (E-F). (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Correspondence, 1924 (G). (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Correspondence, 1924 (H-I-J). (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Correspondence, 1924 (K-L). (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Correspondence, 1924 (M). (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Correspondence, 1924 (N-O). (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Correspondence, 1924 (P-Q). (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Correspondence, 1924 (R). (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Correspondence, 1924 (S). (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Correspondence, 1924 (T-U-V). (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Correspondence, 1924 (W-X-Y-Z). (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Correspondence, 1929 (D). (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Customer Accounts Ledger, 1883-1894. (Volume 2)
- Customer Accounts Ledger, 1894-1902. (Volume 3)
- Customer Accounts Ledger, 1901-1904. (Volume 4)
- Day Book (Journal "B"), 12 April 1879 - 3 September 1890. (Volume 5)
- Description and Preliminary Financial Anaylsis, 1989. (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Diary of Esek Steere, 1852. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Diary of Esek Steere, 1864. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Diary of Esek Steere, 1865. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Diary of Esek Steere, 1870. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Diary of Esek Steere, 1874. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Diary of Esek Steere, 1876. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Diary of Esek Steere, 1878, 1884. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Diary of Esek Steere, 1890. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Diary of Esek Steere, 1893. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Diary of Esek Steere, 1895 (January 1 - April 15). (Box 3, Folder 10)
- "Early Development of the Steam Engine" by Marvin T. Broyhill, 1991. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Economic and Social Benefits of the AIW Visitor Complex, 1990. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Equipment Advertisements. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Estate of Albert Lippett Steere. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Estate of Albert Lippett Steere. (Box 11)
- Facade Incentive Grants Program. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Farquhar Machinery (York, PA). (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Federal Rehabilitation Tax Credits. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Genealogical Notes - Armstrong. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Genealogical Notes - Steere. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Historic Petersburg Foundation. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- History. (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Hopewell Furnace National Historic Site. (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Introduction to the Appomattox Iron Works, 1989. (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Knight Foundry (Sutter Creek, CA) 1990. (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Mechanics' Magazine, 12 April 1834. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- National Recovery Administration, 1935. (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Orders from Customers, July-October 1938 (A-O). (Box 5, Folder 1-15)
- Orders from Customers, July-October 1938 (P-Z). (Box 6, Folder 1-6)
- Petersburg's Commercial Souvenir (copy), 1907?. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Petersburg Iron Works - Receipt, 1889. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Petersburg Urban Enterprise Zone Program. (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Photographs. (Box 9-10)
- Photograph - Petersburg Street Scene. (Box 11)
- Photos and Commentary. (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Postcards. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Price Sheets, 1955-1956 (A). (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Price Sheets, 1955-1956 (M). (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Price Sheets, 1955-1956 (S). (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
- Price Sheets, 1955-1956 (T-U-V). (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Price Sheets, 1955-1956 (W). (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Progress-Index Article, 15 June 1958. (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Project Plans and Specifications, 1990. (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Projected Income and Expenses, 1990. (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Proposed Development, 1990. (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Receipts, 1938-1939 (A-Z). (Box 7, Folder 1-19)
- Report on Nos. 20-28 West Old Street, 1964, 1990. (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Reports (The Mercantile Agency credit reports), 1912-1918 (A-Z). (Box 8, Folder 2-16)
- Sloss Furnaces (Birmingham, AL). (Box 8, Folder 17)
- "The Social Effects of the Industrial Revolution" by George Pilarinos, 1992. (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Steam Engine Projects From "The Young Mechanic". (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Steel and Alexander (Petersburg, Va.) - Receipts, 1896, 1900. (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Tappey and Steel (Petersburg, Va.) - Receipt, 1887. (Box 8, Folder 21)
- Taxes, 1968-1970. (Box 8, Folder 22)
- Titus Iron Works - Pattern Numbering Book. (Box 8, Folder 23)
- Videotape (Beta) - Project Overview Footage, February 1992. (Box 11)
- Videotape (Beta) - "Thursday at the Works" - Fat Ammons Band. (Box 11)
- Weekly Time Book, 13 May 1932 - 15 March 1935. (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Weekly Time Book, 22 March 1935 - 31 December 1937. (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Weekly Time Book, 7 January 1938 - 15 November 1940. (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Weekly Time Book, 27 November 1940 - 10 September 1943. (Box 12, Folder 4)